A Finding Aid to the Los Angeles Art Association Records, 1922-1990, in the Archives of American Art AAA.losangea
Archives of American Art
Los Angeles Art Association records
1922-1990
AAA.losangea
Archives of American Art
12.6 Linear feet
The Los Angeles Art Association records measure 12.6 linear feet and date from 1922-1990. Almost a third of the collection consists of artists’ files containing a wide variety of materials documenting the association’s relationship with numerous California and international artists. Also found are ten scrapbooks documenting exhibitions and events over the course of 50 years, administrative files, correspondence, subject files, exhibition files, financial and legal records, printed material, and photographic material depicting artists, events, and artwork. Scattered files of Executive Director Helen Wurdemann’s are also found throughout the collection.
Los Angeles Art Association.
Biographical/Historical note
Originally founded as the Museum Patrons Association in 1925, the Los Angeles Art Association (LAAA) supported California artists and played an integral role in developing the Los Angeles art community.
The original intent of the Museum Patrons Association was to purchase works of art for the Los Angeles Museum of History, Science and Art. In 1933, the organization separated from the museum and was renamed the Los Angeles Art Association with a primary goal to connect to the broader Los Angeles art community through exhibitions, limited sales, rentals, events, and education. In 1944, with Helen Wurdemann (1892-1988) as Executive Director, the LAAA began to focus more on contemporary local artists, providing a place for the Southern California “hard-edge” abstractionist movement to flourish. In 1951, California painter Lorser Feitelson curated an exhibition of Hans Burkhardt, the LAAA's first solo exhibition of a local artist. Throughout its existence and continuing today, the LAAA has served as a place for arts education, outreach, and community-from its representation of artists studying under the GI bill between 1953 and 1965, to its participation in Monday night art-walks after its move to “Gallery Row” in 1960.
Scope and Contents note
The Los Angeles Art Association records measure 12.6 linear feet and date from 1922-1990. Almost a third of the collection consists of artists’ files containing a wide variety of materials documenting the association’s relationship with numerous California and international artists. Also found are ten scrapbooks documenting exhibitions and events over the course of 50 years, administrative files, correspondence, subject files, exhibition files, financial and legal records, printed material, and photographic material depicting artists, events, and artwork. Scattered files of Executive Director Helen Wurdemann’s are also found throughout the collection.
Administrative records include board of trustees’ meeting minutes, membership correspondence, materials relating to publicity, visitor and artist registers, founding documents, and files on the history of the organization. Files about or created by Executive Director Helen Wurdemann are also found.
Correspondence, including greeting cards and notes, documents the LAAA’s relationship with artists, other associations, museums, and collectors. Hans Burkhardt, Emil J. Kosa Jr., Roger Kuntz, Stanton MacDonald-Wright, Arnold Menches, and Peter Selz are among the correspondents.
Subject files compiled and maintained by the LAAA document special interests, events, and projects. There are files for various arts organizations, Stendhal Gallery, and the Watts Towers Commission.
Exhibition files are found for “Loan Exhibition of International Art” (1937), “Photographs of the George Eastman House Collection 1840-1915” (1968), "Independent Artists of Los Angeles" (1923), and "Top Flight Artists of Southern California" (1941), among others.
Almost a third of the collection consists of artists’ files documenting the LAAA’s relationship with many California and international artists over the years. Files are varied but often include artists’ biographical information, resumes, photographs, price lists, artist statements, and printed materials. Artists include Hans Burkhardt, Jules Engel, and Jack Zajac, among many others.
Financial and legal records consist of daily and exhibition ledgers, art rental and sales files, audit reports and financial statements, billing receipts, bankruptcy legal papers, a prints price list, and miscellaneous financial notes.
Printed material consists of museum and LAAA bulletins, clippings, art school catalogs and brochures, exhibition announcements and catalogs, bulletins and newsletters from other organizations, periodicals, proofs of the “Loan Exhibition of International Art” (1937) exhibition catalog, and a limited edition copy of the book, Paintings by William Merritt Chase signed to the LAAA by B. M. Newhouse.
Photographs, slides, negatives, and copy prints depict LAAA events and gallery openings, artists and people, Executive Director Helen Wurdemann, and works of art by various artists. There are also photographs for publications and a photograph album of artwork by Douglass Parshall.
Ten scrapbooks document LAAA events and exhibitions through clippings, articles, photographs, notes and annotations, announcements, and printed materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Los Angeles Art Association records were donated to the Archives of American in 1990 and 1991 by Richard Campbell of the Los Angeles Art Association.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives’ Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 9 series. Records are generally arranged by material type and chronologically thereafter.
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1925-1989 (Box 1; 0.75 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1933-1990 (Boxes 1-2; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1924-1987 (Box 2; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 4: Exhibition Files, 1923-1982 (Boxes 2-3; 0.45 linear feet)
Series 5: Artists' Files, 1926-1986 (Boxes 3-6; 3.6 linear feet)
Series 6: Financial and Legal Records, 1932-1987 (Boxes 6-8; 1.6 linear feet)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1922-1987 (Boxes 8-9; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographic Materials, 1925-1980 (Boxes 9-10, 13; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 9: Scrapbooks, 1934-1985 (Boxes 10-12, 14; 2.8 linear feet)
Burkhardt, Hans Gustav, 1904-1994; Engel, Jules; George Eastman House; Kosa, Emil Jean, 1903-1968; Kuntz, Roger, 1926-1975; Macdonald-Wright, Stanton, 1890-1973; Menches, Arnold; Selz, Peter Howard, 1919-; Stendahl Art Galleries.; Watts Towers Commission.; Wurdemann, Helen; Zajac, Jack, 1929-; Art--Exhibitions--California--Los Angeles; Art--Societies, etc.--California--Los Angeles; Artists--California--Los Angeles; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Visitors books
- Administrative Records, 1925-1989; Series 1; 0.75 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Administrative records document the founding, history, and ongoing functions of the Los Angeles Art Association. Included is an address book and calendar, an award from the American Red Cross, as well as applications for employment with LAAA and applications for fellowships and various scholarships. Also found are board of trustees’ meeting minutes, membership lists and membership materials, publicity materials, visitor and artist registers, materials relating to the history of the LAAA, by-laws, and articles of incorporation. Additionally, there are scattered materials relating to Executive Director Helen Wurdemann’s activities over the course of her 40-year tenure, including an agenda book, address book, articles and clippings about Wurdemann, and obituary.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Activity File, 1959-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Address Book, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agenda Book, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Applications, Employment, 1965-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Applications, Scholarships and Fellowships, 1949-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Award, American Red Cross, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - By-Laws, Articles of Incorporation, and Prospectus, 1931-1933, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - History of LAAA, 1934-1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Meeting Minutes, Board of Trustees, 1925-1983 (Box 1, Folder 9-13)
  - Membership Lists, 1955-1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Membership Materials and Request Letters, 1958-1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Publicity, Drafts and Annotated Articles, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Publicity, LAAA Lecture Information, 1956-1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Visitor and Artist Registers, 1957-1971 (Box 1, Folder 18-21)
  - Helen Wunderman Articles, 1942-1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Helen Wunderman Articles, Clippings, and Notes, 1954-1987 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Helen Wunderman Agenda Book, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Helen Wunderman Obituary, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Correspondence, 1933-1990; Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Correspondence consists primarily of letters, notes, and cards received from artists, galleries, and other art associations and organizations. Also included is correspondence regarding LAAA’s Earl Mansion location near Otis Art Institute, as well as correspondence from the Unemployment Reserves Commission in 1938. Executive Director Helen Wurdemann also received many letters and cards of congratulations in 1954 for being honored for her work with LAAA at a Masquers Club banquet in Hollywood.
  - Earl Property, 1938-1944 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Helen Wurdemann, Letters and Cards, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Unemployment Reserves Commission, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Greeting Cards, 1964-1986 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - General Correspondence, undated, 1933-1959 (Box 1, Folder 30-33)
  - General Correspondence, 1950-1990 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
- Subject Files, 1924-1987; Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet Box 2
  Subject files covering a variety of special topics and projects were compiled by the LAAA and have been kept in their original order. There are files concerning the California Arts Council, a project to create a directory of artists in Southern California, other organizations and art associations, the Stendhal Gallery, California Landscape, and the Watts Tower Commission project. Individual files may include clippings, notes, lists, announcements, letters, photographs, newsletters, and brochures.
  This series is arranged by subject.
  - Artist List, Directory, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - California Arts Council, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - California Landscape, circa 1931 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Laguna Beach, circa 1930, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Los Angeles Art Museum Fund, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Los Angeles County Museum, 1924-1940 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Organizations, 1953-1985 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Prints to Order, 1968-1987 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Proposed Projects, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Shana Cruse, L. A. County Art Museum Council, 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Show Photographers, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Southern California Academy of Fine Arts, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Stendhal Gallery, 1930-1941 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Subjective Classicism, Post Surrealism, 1938-1941 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - UCLA Art Council, 1957-1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Watts Towers Commission, 1960-1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Exhibition Files, 1923-1982; Series 4; 0.45 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  Exhibition files are found for various LAAA exhibitions, including the 1937 “Loan Exhibition of International Art” which featured such works as Pablo Picasso’s “Woman With Blue Turban,” Marcel Duchamp’s “Nude Descending the Stairs,” and Salvador Dali’s “L’eco Nostalgic,” and saw more than 200,000 visitors; "Independent Artists of Los Angeles" (1923); "Top Flight Artists of Southern California" (1941); and others.
  - "Independent Artists of Los Angeles" (1923) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "Whistler's 'Portrait of the Artist's Mother'" (1933) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Loan Exhibition of International Art" (1937) (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - "Top Flight Artists of Southern California" (1941) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "What's New" (1946) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Photography Exhibitions, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Various Exhibitions, undated, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
  - Various Exhibitions, 1943-1982 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
- Artists' Files, 1926-1986; Series 5; 3.6 Linear feet Boxes 3-6
  Artist files contain a variety of mateirals, such as resumes, correspondence, exhibition catalogs, clippings, lists, announcements, photographs, and slides of work. Files are found for Hans Burkhardt, Charles P. Cross, Janet Culbertson, Jules Engel, Duane Loppnow, Michael O'Mara, Dorothy Orr, Richard Poole, Joseph D. Portanova, Carol Tolin, Antonio Tonon, and Jack Zajac, among others.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by name of artist. Some files are devoted to a single artist, but most are devoted to multiple artists, and filed by letter of the alphabet.
  - Artists' Biographical Information, A-B, circa 1950s-circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Artists' Biographical Information, C-G, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Artists' Biographical Information, S-W, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - A, 1940s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 9-12)
  - B, 1929-1986 (Box 3, Folder 13-17)
  - Brigante, Nick, 1963-1985 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Burkhardt, Hans, 1957-1966 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - C, circa 1930-1983 (Box 3, Folder 20-22)
  - Cross, Charles P., 1964-1970 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Culbertson, Janet, 1966-1973 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - D, circa 1934-circa 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - E, circa 1935-circa 1978 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Engel, Jules, 1960-1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - F, 1928-1980 (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
  - G, 1930-circa 1978 (Box 4, Folder 10-13)
  - H, 1928-1980 (Box 4, Folder 14-16)
  - I, 1936-1976 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - J, 1931-1980 (Box 4, Folder 18-20)
  - K, 1931-1981 (Box 4, Folder 21-23)
  - L, 1926-1979 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Loppnow, Duane, circa 1970s (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - M, 1929-1981 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - N, 1934-1979 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
  - O, 1928-1982 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - O'Mara, Michael, 1963-1970 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Orr, Dorothy, 1974-1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - P, 1929-1979 (Box 5, Folder 12-15)
  - Poole, Richard, 1966-1973 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Portanova, Joseph D., 1956-1974 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Q, 1966-1977 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - R, 1930-1977 (Box 5, Folder 19-20)
  - Reep, Edward, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - S, 1928-1982 (Box 6, Folder 1-6)
  - T, 1961-1979 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
  - Tolin, Carol, 1974-1980 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Tonon, Antonio, 1968-1973 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - V, 1932-1973 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - W, circa 1929-circa 1980 (Box 6, Folder 12-16)
  - Y, 1958-1964 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Z, undated, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Zajac, Jack, 1967-1977 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Financial and Legal Records, 1932-1987; Series 6; 1.6 Linear feet Boxes 6-8, 13
  Financial and legal records include financial and exhibition ledgers, receipts and bills paid, an audit report, financial notes, art loan paperwork, and art rental/sales paperwork.
  - Art Rental Gallery Reports, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Art Rental and Sales Paperwork, 1947-1972 (Box 6, Folder 21-23)
  - Art Rental and Sales Paperwork, 1967-1982 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Audit Report and Financial Statements, 1936, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Bankruptcy Legal Papers, 1977-1979 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Billing Receipts, 1962-1987 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Ledgers, Exhibition Logs, 1954-1982 (Box 7, Folder 6-14)
  - Ledgers, 1933-1966 (Box 7, Folder 15-21)
    Oversized ledger housed in Box 13
  - Ledgers, 1967-1980 (Box 8, Folder 1-7)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Notes, 1952-1978 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Monthly Bills Paid, 1932-1935 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Prints Price List, circa 1964 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Oversized Ledger from Box 7, 1960-1961 (Box 13)
- Printed Material, 1922-1987; Series 7; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 8-9
  Printed material includes art museum and gallery bulletins, art school catalogs and brochures, clippings mentioning LAAA as well as general clippings, gallery exhibition announcements, organization bulletins and newsletters, periodicals and magazines, as well as unannotated proof sheets for the catalog of the “Loan Exhibition of International Art” (1937). Also included is a limited edition print of the book, Paintings by William Merritt Chase signed to LAAA by B. M. Newhouse.
  - Paintings by William Merritt Chase, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Bulletins, Art Institute of Chicago, 1944-1954 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Bulletins, City Art Museum of St. Louis, Los Angeles County Museum, and Museum of Modern Art, 1943-1959 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Bulletins, Cleveland Museum of Art, 1968-1979 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Bulletins, Honolulu Academy of Arts, 1945-1951 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Bulletins, Los Angeles Art Association, 1934-1937 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Bulletins, Philadelphia Museum, 1940-1961 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Catalogs and Brochures, Art Schools, 1925-1976 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, LAAA and Galleries, 1930-1961 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, LAAA Exhibitions, 1957-1966 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, Stendhal Gallery, 1924-1941 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, 1922-1987 (Box 8, Folder 22-25)
  - Clippings, 1926-1984 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
  - Gallery Exhibition Announcements, 1958-1971 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, Galleries, 1935-1986 (Box 9, Folder 5-7)
  - Museum Exhibition Catalogs, undated, 1928-1984 (Box 9, Folder 8-11)
  - Organization Bulletins and Newsletters, 1927, 1959-1986 (Box 9, Folder 12-14)
  - Periodicals, 1936-1977 (Box 9, Folder 15-16)
  - Proofs, Exhibition Catalog ("Loan Exhibition of International Art"), 1937 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Photographs, 1925-1980; Series 8; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 9-10, 13
  Photographic materials consist of black and white original photographs, copy prints, color snapshots, safety negatives, color slides, and a photograph album. Most of the photographs are of works of art. There are also images of LAAA events and exhibition openings, Helen Wurdemann, artists and other persons, as well as photographs intended for publications. There are images of artwork in the William Presten Harrison Collection and one photograph album containing photographs of portraits by Douglass Parshall.
  - LAAA Events and Gallery Openings, circa 1954-1974 (Box 9, Folder 18-20)
    Oversized photographs housed in Box 13
  - Photographs of Helen Wurdemann, undated, 1954-1974 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Artists and People, circa 1950s-circa 1960s (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Los Angeles County Museum, "New" Building Rendering, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Photographs for Publications, circa 1966 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Photographs of Works of Art (Box 10)
    - Maud Dagget, circa 1930 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Roger Kuntz, 1949-1952 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - David Leneman, circa 1949 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Douglas McClellan, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Warren Newcombe, circa 1930s (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Art Starr, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - William Preston Harrison Collection, circa 1925-circa 1930s (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - William M. Chase, 1925-1934 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Donated to LAAA, 1934-1935 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - For Publication, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Artwork, undated, 1933-1978 (Box 10, Folder 11-17)
  - Oversized Douglass Parshall Photo Album, Artwork, circa 1934 (Box 13)
  - Oversized Photographs, Artwork from Box 10, undated (Box 13)
  - Oversized Photographs, LAAA Events and Gallery Openings from Box 9, 1966 (Box 13)
- Scrapbooks, 1934-1985; Series 9; 2.8 Linear feet Boxes 10-12, 14
  This series includes 10 scrapbooks of clippings, gallery announcements and exhibitions, correspondence, photographs, and notes and annotations.
  This series is arranged chronologically according to original order. Some scrapbooks have been disassembled and kept in their original order, while others have been kept intact.
  - Scrapbook, 1933-1934 (Box 10, Folder 18-20)
  - Scrapbook, 1941-1946 (Box 10, Folder 21-24)
  - Scrapbook, 1946-1951 (Box 14)
  - Scrapbook, 1951-1955 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook, 1956-1959 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook, 1961-1974 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook, 1975-1985 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook, 1960 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook, 1960-1969 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook, 1960-1975 (Box 12)